He originated from Athens aristocracy and the family's fortune
enabled him to devote his life to philosophy and searching for knowledge.
The name Plato is said to be a nickname he received in his youth when he devoted himself to wrestling
- A name he chose to keep instead of the birth name Aristokles.
He must have been in his 20s when he was occupied in the circle around Socrates.
For seven years he studied his teachings, before Socrates finally executed.
At that time Plato was the foremost of the disciples,
And anyone who would also pass on and develop philosophy.
With Pythagoras as a model, he decided after Socrates' death to start his own philosophy.
The school went under the name Academy (by Akademos, a hero in Greek mythology)
And came to become the role model for today's universities and colleges.
Here, teaching and research was conducted, and in the premises there were lecture rooms, libraries and housing.
The school came to live as an important institution for education for over 900 years before it was closed
By the Byzantine Emperor Justinian I who considered that philosophy was a threat to the Christian faith.
Plato also began writing books on the topic of philosophy.
These texts all revolved around Socrates who discussed moral and political concepts,
But what starts as a speech at Pythagoras will develop into ideas or forms at Plato.
According to Plato, what we with our senses perceive as reality is not the true reality
Without only a shadow image of it - this when our soul is locked in a body with imperfect knowledge organs.
The idea of ideas can be explained by thinking about a circle.
A drawn circle - thus something that exists in our perceived reality - can never be perfect.
If you look carefully enough, you will always find someone small defect.
What all drawn circles that have ever existed have in common is that they refer to the perfect circle.
But the perfect circle does not exist in our world, it is an abstraction.
The perfect circle - the idea of the circle - is outside time and space.
It is non-material and eternal, and is perfect to its definition.
In addition, there is only one circle idea.
And even though the perfect circle does not exist in our world
In the reality we experience with our minds-the world of mind-everything is non-perfect and temporary.
Then there is another reality that has its existence beyond time and room
And that is not available to our minds - the world of ideas.
Here everything is perfect and eternal, and here is everything's shape, template or origin.
Plato now wonders what all people have in common, what it is that makes us just people.
Individuals change - grow up, aging and die, but the concept of human remains the same.
According to Plato we are humans because we have part of man's idea
In the same way that the drawn circle has part in the idea of the circle.
Everything that exists in our world is only worse copies of a perfect abstraction.
It is because we humans have the ability to see through reason and thinking the idea of things
which we can also identify and understand them.
This reasoning makes Plato an idealist.
Idealism is a philosophical view where it is believed that reality is basically made up of something non-material
- An idea or consciousness.
This is in contrast to realism or materialism that believes that reality is mainly material.
To explain the idea of idea, Plato Cave Like - a famous Allegori created where he paints a picture
of a couple of prisoners who interpret shadows on the wall as reality.
We are all these prisoners, said Plato, caught in our world of mind.
What we believe is reality is, in fact, only shadows of it.
In a cave, a group of people are imprisoned with their faces facing the inner wall.
They have been sitting there all their lives, and are bound so they have never seen anything other than this particular wall.
Based on the opening of the cave, the sun's rays shine in and throw shadows on the wall in front of the prisoners.
These shadows are the only object that the prisoners have ever seen,
and will for them constitute reality.
It is around this shadow world of the prisoners' lives, and they talk to each other about the things they see.
If any of the prisoners were to detach themselves and escape into the real world
- So he would immediately be dazzled by the sun, as he had never seen before.
When his eyes got used to the light could see that what he previously believed was the act of shadows only,
or worse copies, of something more real.
We are all these prisoners, said Plato, captures in our own world of mind.
What we believe is reality is, in fact, only shadows of it.
Unlike everyday people who only had performances.
Only the most intelligent would be trained to philosophers, an education that went on to the age of 35.
Then followed 15 years of internship before being mature at 50.
He argued here for both class trips and complete gender equality -
Two extremely radical thoughts for their time.
The philosophers were not allowed to have private ownership so as not to be attracted to abuse their power to personal gain.
Everything was owned jointly and one would live in a collective under simple conditions.
The philosopher was not allowed to have any family but the state would arrange big parties
where philosophers of both sexes would meet so that children could be bred.
These children would then be taken from the parents immediately after birth and raised by the state.
No one was told who your child was, so as not to benefit them.
The children would thus consider all of their own age as their siblings
And all in adulthood as their parents - and thus want everyone well.
His purpose with this was to overcome the human selfishness
through a system based on social equality.
The goal was to get a people who would do well in war,
Clearly inspired by the nearby warrior state Sparta.
Plato's political ideas have influenced many of the totalitarian left and right ideologies
which characterized the 20th century.
He must have tried on several occasions to realize his political utopia, but without much success.